<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Job | EV / The modelers</title>
    <link>https://www.evmodelers.org/tag/job/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.evmodelers.org/tag/job/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Job</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.evmodelers.org/media/icon_hu01cac6525d55afbbab85fa5aa9513d33_105925_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Job</title>
      <link>https://www.evmodelers.org/tag/job/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc Position - Tabular foundation models for epidemic modeling</title>
      <link>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025postdocdiscoreel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025postdocdiscoreel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We will be hiring a postdoctoral researcher to work full-time on the DiscoReel project. The postdoc will work on foundation models for tabular data in epidemic modeling. The candidate should have a background in computer science and previous experience in designing and traning large models. No prior experience in epidemiology is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The position is likely to start in early 2026 and last 1 year, renewable. More info soon. If you fit the profile and are interested in having more information please contact Eugenio Valdano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply for the position please use &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/kZs1gLBEPVKuXo5KA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. The position will be filled as soon a suitable candidate is found.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internship - Causal analysis of PrEP and sexual behavior in MSM</title>
      <link>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025interncausal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025interncausal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are opening an internship position at Inserm (Paris) to work on the causal analysis of PrEP uptake and sexual behavior change among MSM, as part of the PP-IMPACT project funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://anrs.fr/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANRS-MIE&lt;/a&gt;. The intern will work under the supervision of Eugenio Valdano and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ckassaad.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Charles Assaad&lt;/a&gt;, expert in causal inference. The analysis will use observational cohort data from Portugal and France to identify bidirectional causal links between behavior and PrEP adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to have more information please contact either E. Valdano or C. Assaad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply for the internship please use &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/oJGwUzQaGxwM9GLKA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. The position will be filled as soon a suitable candidate is found.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internship - Tabular foundation models for epidemic modeling</title>
      <link>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025intern/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.evmodelers.org/job/2025intern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are looking for an intern to apply foundation models for tabular data to modeling spatially structured epidemics. Candidates will be 1st-year or 2nd-year master students in computer science, machine learning, physics or applied mathematics. The starting date can be from September 2025, onwards. Internships typically last 4 to 6 months. Check out our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.02.24.25322795v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;relevant publication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to have more information please contact Eugenio Valdano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply for the internship please use &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/oJGwUzQaGxwM9GLKA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. The position will be filled as soon a suitable candidate is found.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
